Last year, I went on my first book tour.
في السنة الماضية سافرت في جولة كتابي الأول.
In 13 months, I flew to 14 countries
في 13 شهرا سافرت إلى 14 دولة
and gave some hundred talks.
وألقيت مايناهز 100 محادثة.
Every talk in every country
كل محادثة في كل دولة
began with an introduction,
تبدآ بمقدمة،
and every introduction began, alas, with a lie:
و للأسف تبدأ كل محادثة بكذبة:
"Taiye Selasi comes from Ghana and Nigeria,"
"تنحدر تايا سيلاسي من غانا ونيجيريا،"
or "Taiye Selasi comes from England and the States."
آو"تنحدر تايا سيلاسي من إنجلترا و الولايات المتحدة."
Whenever I heard this opening sentence,
كلما سمعت هذة الجملة الإفتتاحية،
no matter the country that concluded it --
مهما كانت الدولة التي تنتهي إليها--
England, America, Ghana, Nigeria --
إنجلترا، أمريكا، غانا، نيجيريا--
I thought, "But that's not true."
أفكر " لكن هذا ليس صحيحاً."
Yes, I was born in England and grew up in the United States.
نعم ولدت في إنجلترا وتربيت في أمريكا.
My mum, born in England, and raised in Nigeria,
والدتي ولدت في إنجلترا وتربت في نيجيريا،
currently lives in Ghana.
حاليا تعيش في غانا.
My father was born in Gold Coast, a British colony,
أبي ولد في الساحل الذهبي، وهي مستعمرة بريطانية،
raised in Ghana,
تربى في غانا،
and has lived for over 30 years in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.
وعاش لأكثر من30 سنة في المملكة العربية السعودية.
For this reason, my introducers also called me "multinational."
لهذا يطلق علي من يقدمونني أيضا على أنني " متعددة الجنسيات."
"But Nike is multinational," I thought,
"لكن نايكي متعددة الجنسيات" آعتقد ذلك،
"I'm a human being."
" أنا إنسانة."
Then, one fine day, mid-tour,
وفي يوم جميل،في منتصف جولتي،
I went to Louisiana, a museum in Denmark
ذهبت إلى لويزيانا وهو متحف في الدنمارك
where I shared the stage with the writer Colum McCann.
حيث تقاسمت االمسرح مع الكاتب كولوم ماكان.
We were discussing the role of locality in writing,
كنا نناقش دور المحلية في الكتابة،
when suddenly it hit me.
عندما فجأة تنبهت.
I'm not multinational.
أنا لست متعدد الجنسيات.
I'm not a national at all.
لست مواطنة أصلا.
How could I come from a nation?
فكيف لي أن أتي من دولة ؟
How can a human being come from a concept?
كيف للإنسان آن يأتي من مفهوم ؟
It's a question that had been bothering me for going on two decades.
إنه سؤال لازال يضايقني منذ عقدين مضيا.
From newspapers, textbooks, conversations,
من الجرائد، الكتب المدرسية، المحادثات
I had learned to speak of countries
تعلمت الحديث عن الدول
as if they were eternal, singular, naturally occurring things,
كما لوأنها أشياء أبدية،فردية، طبيعية،
but I wondered:
لكني أتعجب:
to say that I came from a country
لأقول أني أنحدر من دولة
suggested that the country was an absolute,
فهذا يعني أن البلاد كانت شيئا مطلقا،
some fixed point in place in time,
بعض النقط المحددة في المكان والزمان،
a constant thing, but was it?
شيء ثابت، لكن هل كانت كذلك؟
In my lifetime, countries had disappeared -- Czechoslovakia;
في حياتي، اختفت بلدان --تشيكوسلوفاكيا،
appeared -- Timor-Leste; failed -- Somalia.
وظهرت--تيمور ليشتي; فشلت -- الصومال
My parents came from countries that didn't exist when they were born.
أتى والدي من بلدين لم يكونا موجودين حين ولدا.
To me, a country -- this thing that could be born, die, expand, contract --
بانسبة لي ،الدولة-- هي شيء قد يولد،يموت،يتوسع،يتقلص--
hardly seemed the basis for understanding a human being.
بالكاد يبدو هذا كأساس لفهم الكائن البشري.
And so it came as a huge relief to discover the sovereign state.
لذلك فمن المريح جدا اكتشاف مفهوم الدولة السيادية.
What we call countries are actually
ما نطلق عليها دول هي في الواقع
various expressions of sovereign statehood,
تعبيرات مختلفة من دولة ذات سيادة،
an idea that came into fashion only 400 years ago.
الفكره التي أصبحت موضة منذ 400 سنة فقط.
When I learned this, beginning my masters degree in international relations,
حين علمت بهذا،في بداية تحضيري لشهادة الماجيستير في العلاقات الدولية،
I felt a sort of surge of relief.
شعرت نوعاً من موجة من الارتياح.
It was as I had suspected.
كان كما لو كنت مشتبهاً بها.
History was real, cultures were real,
التاريخ كان حقيقياً،الثقافة كانت حقيقية،
but countries were invented.
لكن الدول كانت مخترعة،
For the next 10 years, I sought to re- or un-define myself,
في السنوات العشر التي تلت،ارتأيت أن أعيد تعريف نفسي أو أن ألغي التعريف عنها،
my world, my work, my experience,
أو عن عالمي، وظيفتي،تجربتي،
beyond the logic of the state.
إلى ما وراء منطق الدولة.
In 2005, I wrote an essay, "What is an Afropolitan,"
سنة 2005،كتبت مقالاً،"ماهو الآفروبولتن"،
sketching out an identity that privileged culture over country.
محاولة رسم هوية آثرت الثقافة عل الدولة.
It was thrilling how many people could relate to my experience,
كان الأمر مثيرا كيف أن الكثير من الناس كانت لهم نفس التجربة،
and instructional how many others didn't buy my sense of self.
وكم كان ملهما كيف أن العديد من الناس لم يتبنوا رؤيتي للذات.
"How can Selasi claim to come from Ghana," one such critic asked,
"كيف لسيلاسي أن تدعي أنها تنحدرمن غانا،" تساءل أحدهم ناقدا،
"when she's never known the indignities
"وهي لن تعيش أبدا صعوبات
of traveling abroad on a Ghanian passport?"
السفر خارجاً بجواز سفر غيني؟"
Now, if I'm honest,
الآن، لو كنت صادقة،
I knew just what she meant.
فقد علمت مالذي كانت تعنيه.
I've got a friend named Layla who was born and raised in Ghana.
لدي صديقة اسمها ليلى ولدت و ترعرعت في غانا.
Her parents are third-generation Ghanians of Lebanese descent.
والداها ينتميان للجيل الثالث من الغانيين من أصول لبنانية.
Layla, who speaks fluent Twi, knows Accra like the back of her hand,
ليلى والتي تتحدث التوي بطلاقة ، تعرف آكرا مثل الجزء الخلفي من يدها،
but when we first met years ago, I thought, "She's not from Ghana."
ولكن عندما التقينا للمرة الآولى منذ سنوات، اعتقدت،"أنها ليست من غانا."
In my mind, she came from Lebanon,
في بالي،فهي من لبنان،
despite the patent fact that all her formative experience
على الرغم من أن الواقع واضح أن كل تجاربها التكوينية
took place in suburban Accra.
وقعت في ضواحي آكرا.
I, like my critics,
أنا ، مثل نقادي،
was imagining some Ghana where all Ghanaians had brown skin
تصورت غانا حيث كل الغانيين ذووبشرة داكنة
or none held U.K. passports.
أو حيث لا أحد يملك جوزات سفر بريطانية.
I'd fallen into the limiting trap
كنت قد سقطت في فخ الحدود
that the language of coming from countries sets --
أن مجموعة الجمل التي تحمل معنى" قادم من"--
the privileging of a fiction, the singular country,
وتفضيل الخيال،و الدولة الفردية،
over reality: human experience.
على الواقع : التجربة الإنسانية.
Speaking with Colum McCann that day, the penny finally dropped.
التحدث مع كولوم ماكان ذلك اليوم ، كان النقطة المضيئة.
"All experience is local," he said.
"كل التجارب محلية،"كذلك قال.
"All identity is experience," I thought.
قلت في نفسي"كل الهويات هي تجارب"،
"I'm not a national," I proclaimed onstage.
"أنا لست مواطنة،"أعلنت من المنصة.
"I'm a local. I'm multi-local."
"أنا محلية. وأنا متعددة المحلية"
See, "Taiye Selasi comes from the United States," isn't the truth.
أرأيتم،" تاي سبلاسي تنحدر من الولايات المتحدة" ليس صحيحا.
I have no relationship with the United States,
ليست لي علاقة بالولايات المتحدة،
all 50 of them, not really.
كل الولايات ال50،ليس صحيحا.
My relationship is with Brookline, the town where I grew up;
علاقتي هي مع بروكلين، المدينة التي نشأت فيها،
with New York City, where I started work;
مع مدينة نيويورك، حيث بدأت العمل،
with Lawrenceville, where I spend Thanksgiving.
مع رينسيفسل، حيث أمضيت عيد الشكر.
What makes America home for me is not my passport or accent,
ما يجعل أمريكا وطنا لي ليس جواز سفري أو لكنتي،
but these very particular experiences
بل هذه التجارب الخاصة جدا
and the places they occur.
والآماكن التي وقعت فيها.
Despite my pride in Ewe culture,
على الرغم فخورة بكوني من ثقافة إيو،
the Black Stars, and my love of Ghanaian food,
والنجوم السود، و حبي للطعام الغيني،
I've never had a relationship with the Republic of Ghana, writ large.
لم تكن لي علاقة أبدا مع جمهورية غانا، بالمطلق.
My relationship is with Accra, where my mother lives,
علاقتي هي مع آكرا حيث تعيش والدتي،
where I go each year,
حيث أذهب كل سنة،
with the little garden in Dzorwulu where my father and I talk for hours.
مع الحديقة الصغيرة في دزورولو حيث أتحدث مع والدي لساعات.
These are the places that shape my experience.
هذه هي الآماكن التي تشكل تجاربي.
My experience is where I'm from.
تجربتي هي من أين أتيت.
What if we asked, instead of "Where are you from?" --
ماذا لو استبدلنا السؤال : " من أي بلد أنت؟"
"Where are you a local?"
ب" من أين أنت محليا"؟
This would tell us so much more about who and how similar we are.
سيقول لنا الجواب الكثير عمن نحن،وكيف أننا متشابهون.
Tell me you're from France, and I see what, a set of clichés?
قل لي أنت من فرنسا،ماذا سأرى؟ مجموعة من الصور النمطية؟
Adichie's dangerous single story, the myth of the nation of France?
ديتشي قصة وحيدة و خطيرة، أسطورة الأمة الفرنسية؟
Tell me you're a local of Fez and Paris,
أخبرني أنك محليا من فاس و باريس،
better yet, Goutte d'Or, and I see a set of experiences.
والأفضل من ذلك، غوت دور، وسأرى مجموعة من التجارب.
Our experience is where we're from.
تتحدد تجاربنا من الأمكنة التي أتينا منها.
So, where are you a local?
لذلك،من أين أنت محليا؟
I propose a three-step test.
أقترح اختبار الخطوات الثلاث.
I call these the three "R’s": rituals, relationships, restrictions.
وهي: الطقوس، والعلاقات، والقيود.
First, think of your daily rituals, whatever they may be:
آولاً، فكر بطقوسك اليومية، مهما كانت:
making your coffee, driving to work,
تحضير قهوتك،القيلدة نحو عملك،
harvesting your crops, saying your prayers.
حصاد محاصيلك، قرأة صلواتك
What kind of rituals are these?
مانوع هذه الطقوس؟
Where do they occur?
و أين تحصل ؟
In what city or cities in the world do shopkeepers know your face?
في أي مدينة أو مدن يعرفك أصحاب محلات البقالة؟
As a child, I carried out fairly standard suburban rituals in Boston,
عندما كنت طفلة،حملت معي طقوسا معروفة من ضواحي بوسطن،
with adjustments made for the rituals my mother brought from London and Lagos.
مع تعديلات على الطقوس التي جلبتها أمي من لندن و لاغوس.
We took off our shoes in the house,
نخلع أحذيتنا في المنزل،
we were unfailingly polite with our elders,
كنا وبدون كلل مؤدبين مع من يكبرنا سنا،
we ate slow-cooked, spicy food.
نأكل الطعام المطهي ببطء،و الأكل الحار.
In snowy North America, ours were rituals of the global South.
في أمريكا الشمالية ذات الثلوج، كانت طقوسنا من جنوب العالم.
The first time I went to Delhi or to southern parts of Italy,
حينما ذهبت إلى دلهي للمرة الأولى أو للأجزاء الجنوبية لإيطاليا،
I was shocked by how at home I felt.
كنت منهشة كيف أنني فعلا أحسست أنني في وطني.
The rituals were familiar.
كانت الطقوس مألوفة.
"R" number one, rituals.
الطقوس، هي الرقم واحد لدينا.
Now, think of your relationships, of the people who shape your days.
الآن، فكر بعلاقاتك بالناس التي تشكل يومك.
To whom do you speak at least once a week,
مع من تتحدث مرة في الأسبوع على الأقل،
be it face to face or on FaceTime?
سواء كان وجها لوجه أو على الفيس تايم؟
Be reasonable in your assessment;
كن عقلانيا في تقييمك،
I'm not talking about your Facebook friends.
لا أتحدث عن أصدقائك على الفايسبوك.
I'm speaking of the people who shape your weekly emotional experience.
أتحدث عن الناس الذين يشكلون تجربتك العاطفية الأسيوعية.
My mother in Accra, my twin sister in Boston,
والدتي في آكرا،أختي التوأم في بوسطن،
my best friends in New York:
آصدقائي المقربين في نيويورك:
these relationships are home for me.
هذه العلاقات هي الوطن بالنسبة لي.
"R" number two, relationships.
رقمنا الثاني هي العلاقات.
We're local where we carry out our rituals and relationships,
نحن محليون حيث نحمل طقوسنا وعلاقاتنا،
but how we experience our locality
لكن كيفية اختبار محليتنا
depends in part on our restrictions.
تعتمد جزئياً على قيودنا.
By restrictions, I mean, where are you able to live?
أعني بالقيود، أين تستطيع العيش؟
What passport do you hold?
أي جواز تحمل؟
Are you restricted by, say, racism, from feeling fully at home where you live?
هل أنت مقيد،لنقل، بالعنصرية، أو أنك لا تحس أنك في الوطن حيث تعيش؟
By civil war, dysfunctional governance, economic inflation,
بسبب الحرب الأهلية، أو الحكامة غير الجيدة، التضخم الاقتصادي،
from living in the locality where you had your rituals as a child?
من أن تعيش المحلية التي كنت تعيش فيها طقوسك حين كنت طفلا؟
This is the least sexy of the R’s,
هذه هي الخطوة الأقل إثارة بين الخطوات الثلاث،
less lyric than rituals and relationships,
سيكون الكلام عنه قليلا بالمقارنة مع الطقوس والعلاقات،
but the question takes us past "Where are you now?"
لكن السؤال يأخذنا ببعيدا عن "أين أنت الآن؟"
to "Why aren't you there, and why?"
إلى " لم لست هناك، و لماذا؟"
Rituals, relationships, restrictions.
الطقوس، العلاقات، القيود.
Take a piece of paper
خذ قطعة من الورق
and put those three words on top of three columns,
و ضع تلك الكلمات الثلاث على رأس ثلاثة أعمدة،
then try to fill those columns as honestly as you can.
ثم حاول ملء تلك الأعمدة بكل صدق ممكن.
A very different picture of your life in local context,
صوره مختلفة جداً من حياتك في السياق المحلي،
of your identity as a set of experiences,
عن هويتك كمجموعة من النجارب،
may emerge.
قد تظهر.
So let's try it.
لذا دعونا نحاول ذلك.
I have a friend named Olu.
لدي صديق اسمه أولو.
He's 35 years old.
يبلغ من العمر 35 سنة.
His parents, born in Nigeria, came to Germany on scholarships.
ولد والداه في نيجريا، وجاءا إلى ألمانبا عن طريق منحة دراسية.
Olu was born in Nuremberg and lived there until age 10.
ولد أولو في نورمبورغ وعاش حتى سن العاشرة.
When his family moved to Lagos, he studied in London,
حين انتقلت عائلته إلى لاغوس، درس في لندن،
then came to Berlin.
ثم جاء إلى برلين.
He loves going to Nigeria --
يحب أن يذهب إلى نيجيربا--
the weather, the food, the friends --
الجو، والطعام، والأصدقاء--
but hates the political corruption there.
ولكنه يكره الفساد السياسي هناك.
Where is Olu from?
من أين ينحدرأولو ؟
I have another friend named Udo.
لدسي صديق آخر اسمه أودو.
He's also 35 years old.
هو أيضا يبلغ من العمر 35سنة.
Udo was born in Córdoba, in northwest Argentina,
ولد أودو في قرطبة في شمال غرب الآرجنتين،
where his grandparents migrated from Germany, what is now Poland,
حيث هاجر أجداده من ألمانيا، والتي هي بولندا،
after the war.
بعد الحرب.
Udo studied in Buenos Aires, and nine years ago came to Berlin.
درس أودو في بوينس آيرس، وقد عاد قبل 9 سنوات إلى برلين.
He loves going to Argentina -- the weather, the food, the friends --
هو يحب الذهاب إلى الأرجنتين-- الجو،والأكل و الأصدقاء--
but hates the economic corruption there.
ولكنه يكره الفساد الاقتصادي هناك.
Where is Udo from?
من أين ينحدر أودو؟
With his blonde hair and blue eyes, Udo could pass for German,
بشعره الأشقر و عينيه الزرقاوتين، يبدو أودو ألمانيا،
but holds an Argentinian passport, so needs a visa to live in Berlin.
لكنه يحمل جواز سفر أرجنتيني، ويحتاج تأشيرة للعيش في برلين.
That Udo is from Argentina has largely to do with history.
كون أودو من الأرجنتين فهذا أمر متعلق بشكل كبير بالتاريخ.
That he's a local of Buenos Aires and Berlin,
كونه محليا من بوينس أيرس و برلين،
that has to do with life.
فهذا أمر متعلق بالحياة.
Olu, who looks Nigerian, needs a visa to visit Nigeria.
أولو ذو المظهر النيجيري يحتاج لتأشيرة لزيارة نيجريا.
He speaks Yoruba with an English accent,
يتحدث اليوروبا مع لكنة إنجليزية،
and English with a German one.
واإنجليزية بلكنة ألمانية.
To claim that he's "not really Nigerian," though,
الإدعاء بأنه " ليس حقاً نيجريا" في المقابل،
denies his experience in Lagos,
ينفي تجربته في لاغوس،
the rituals he practiced growing up,
و الطقوس التي مارسها خلال حياته،
his relationship with family and friends.
وعلاقته مع عائلته وأصدقائه.
Meanwhile, though Lagos is undoubtedly one of his homes,
وفي الوقت نفسه، على رغم من كون لاغوس هي بالتأكيد أحد أوطانه،
Olu always feels restricted there,
دائما مايشعر أولو بأنه مقيد هناك،
not least by the fact that he's gay.
ليس على الأقل لأنه في الحقيقة شاذ.
Both he and Udo are restricted by the political conditions
كلاهما هو و أودو مقيدان بظروف سياسية
of their parents' countries,
خاصة بدول آبائهم.
from living where some of their most meaningful rituals
من العيش حيث توجد بعض من طقوسهم
and relationships occur.
وعلاقاتهم التي تعني لهم الكثير.
To say Olu is from Nigeria and Udo is from Argentina
يصرفنا القول آن آولو من نيجيريا و آودو من آرجنتين
distracts from their common experience.
عن النظر لتجاربهم المشتركة.
Their rituals, their relationships, and their restrictions are the same.
طقوسهم، و علاقاتهم و قيودهم متشابهة
Of course, when we ask, "Where are you from?"
بالطبع، عندما نسأل، " من أين أنت؟"
we're using a kind of shorthand.
نحن نستخدم نوعا من الاختزال.
It's quicker to say "Nigeria" than "Lagos and Berlin,"
من السهل قول :"نيجريا" عوضا عن "لاغوس و برلين،"
and as with Google Maps, we can always zoom in closer,
وكما هو الحال مع خرائط جوجل يمكننا دائما التقريب
from country to city to neighborhood.
من بلد إلى مدينة إلى حي.
But that's not quite the point.
ولكن هذا ليس تماماً المغزى
The difference between "Where are you from?"
الفرق بين " من أين أنت"
and "Where are you a local?"
و " من أين أنت محليا؟"
isn't the specificity of the answer;
ليست نوعية الجواب،
it's the intention of the question.
إنما هي بنية السؤال.
Replacing the language of nationality with the language of locality asks us
استبدال لغة الجنسية مع اللغة المحلية تتطلب منا
to shift our focus to where real life occurs.
تحويل تركيزنا إلى مكان الذي نعيش فيه حقيقة.
Even that most glorious expression of countryhood, the World Cup,
حتى أن التعبير الآكثر تمجيدا للبلد ، و هوكأس العالم،
gives us national teams comprised mostly of multilocal players.
يعطينا فرق وطنية يتكون معظمها من لاعبين متعددي المحلية.
As a unit of measurement for human experience,
كوحدة قياس لتجارب للتجربة الإنسانية،
the country doesn't quite work.
فإن البلد ليس معيارا دقيقا.
That's why Olu says, "I'm German, but my parents come from Nigeria."
ذلك ما يجعل أولو يقول، "أنا ألماني، لكن والدي ينحدران من نيجيريا."
The "but" in that sentence belies the inflexibility of the units,
"لكن" في تلك الجملة تكذب عدم مرونة الوحدات،
one fixed and fictional entity bumping up against another.
وحدة ثابتة وأخرى خيالية تصطدم ببعضها البعض.
"I'm a local of Lagos and Berlin," suggests overlapping experiences,
" آنا محلي من لوغوس و برلين" تقترح التجارب المتداخلة،
layers that merge together, that can't be denied or removed.
الطبقات التي تدمج معاً ،و التي لايمكن إنكارها أو إزالتها.
You can take away my passport,
يمكنك أن تأخذ مني جواز سفري،
but you can't take away my experience.
لكن لايمكنك أن تآخذ مني تجربتي.
That I carry within me.
تلك التي أحملها معي.
Where I'm from comes wherever I go.
أصلي هو كل مكان أذهب إليه.
To be clear, I'm not suggesting that we do away with countries.
لأكون واضحة،فأنا لا أقترح التخلي عن الدول.
There's much to be said for national history,
هناك الكثير مما يمكن قوله عن التاريخ الوطني،
more for the sovereign state.
وأكثر من ذلك عن الدولة السيادية.
Culture exists in community, and community exists in context.
الثقافة موجودة في المجتمع والمجتمع موجود في السياق.
Geography, tradition, collective memory: these things are important.
الجغرافيا، والتقاليد، والذاكرة الجماعية: هذه الآمور مهمة.
What I'm questioning is primacy.
ماأتساءل بشأنه هي الأولوية.
All of those introductions on tour began with reference to nation,
كل تلك المقدمات في الجولة بدأت بالعودة إلى الأمة،
as if knowing what country I came from would tell my audience who I was.
وكأن معرفة من أي بلد أتيت سيعطي جمهوريفكرة عمن أكون.
What are we really seeking, though, when we ask where someone comes from?
مالذي نسعى إليه حقا،بالمقابل، حسن نسأل من أي بلد ينحدر شخص ما؟
And what are we really seeing when we hear an answer?
و ما الذي نراه حقاً عندما نسمع الجواب؟
Here's one possibility:
وهذا احتمال واحد:
basically, countries represent power.
بالأساس،فالدول تمثل القوة.
"Where are you from?" Mexico. Poland. Bangladesh. Less power.
"من أين أنت؟" المكسيك.بولندا.بنغلاديش.قوة أضعف.
America. Germany. Japan. More power.
أمريكا.ألمانيا.اليابان.قوة أكبر.
China. Russia. Ambiguous.
الصين.روسيا.دول غامضة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's possible that without realizing it, we're playing a power game,
من الممكن، أن نكون من دون أن ندرك بصدد لعب لعبة القوة،
especially in the context of multi-ethnic countries.
خاصة في سياق البلدان متعددة الأعراق.
As any recent immigrant knows,
كما يعلم كل مهاجر جديد،
the question "Where are you from?" or "Where are you really from?"
فالسؤال " من أين أتيت؟" أو" من أين أنت حقيقة؟"
is often code for "Why are you here?"
يكون غالبا شفرة ل" لماذا أنت هنا؟"
Then we have the scholar William Deresiewicz's writing
ثم لدينا كتابة العالم ويليام دراسويس
of elite American colleges.
من نخبة الكليات الآمريكية
"Students think that their environment is diverse
"يعتقد الطلاب أن بيئتهم متنوعة
if one comes from Missouri and another from Pakistan --
إن كان أحدهم من ميسوري والآخر من باكستان--
never mind that all of their parents are doctors or bankers."
فلا يهم إن كان آباؤهم أطباء أو مصرفيين."
I'm with him.
أتفق معه.
To call one student American, another Pakistani,
لإطلاق صفة أمريكي على طالب، وباكستاني على آخر،
then triumphantly claim student body diversity
وبعدها التفاخر بتنوع النسيج الطلابي
ignores the fact that these students are locals of the same milieu.
فهذا يقصي واقع أن هؤلاء الطلبة هم محليون من نفس الوسط.
The same holds true on the other end of the economic spectrum.
وينطبق الشيء نفسه على الطرف الآخر من الطيف الإقتصادي.
A Mexican gardener in Los Angeles and a Nepali housekeeper in Delhi
البستاني المكسيكي في لوس أنجلوس ومدبرة المنزل النيبالية في دلهي
have more in common in terms of rituals and restrictions
لديهم الكثير من القواسم المشتركة من حيث الطقوس والقيود
than nationality implies.
التي تمليها الجنسية.
Perhaps my biggest problem with coming from countries
ربما مشكلتي الكبرى مع القادمين من الدول
is the myth of going back to them.
هي أسطورة العودة إليها.
I'm often asked if I plan to "go back" to Ghana.
كثيرا ما أسأل إن كنت أخطط "للعودة" إلى غانا.
I go to Accra every year, but I can't "go back" to Ghana.
أذهب إلى آكرا كل سنة، لكن لا يمكنني "العودة "إلى غانا.
It's not because I wasn't born there.
ليس لأنني لم أولد هناك.
My father can't go back, either.
لا يستطيع أبي العودة هناك،أيضا.
The country in which he was born,
الدولة التي ولد فيها،
that country no longer exists.
تلك الدولة لم يعد لها وجود.
We can never go back to a place and find it exactly where we left it.
لا يمكن أن نعود لمكان ما ونجده تماما كما تركناه.
Something, somewhere will always have changed,
شيء ما،في مكان ما لا محالة سيتغير،
most of all, ourselves.
الآهم من ذلك كله، أنفسنا.
People.
الناس.
Finally, what we're talking about is human experience,
وفي الآخير مانتحدث عنه هي التجربة الإنسانية،
this notoriously and gloriously disorderly affair.
هذه القضية المعروفة و المجيدة وغير المرتبة.
In creative writing, locality bespeaks humanity.
في الكتابة الإبداعية فالمحلية تنم عن الإنسانية.
The more we know about where a story is set,
كلما عرفنا أكثر على مكان بداية القصة،
the more local color and texture,
كلما بدأنا نتحسس اللون و النسج المحلي،
the more human the characters start to feel,
ونتحسس الإنسانية و الشخصيات بشكل أكبر،
the more relatable, not less.
وكلما أحسسنا بصلة أكبر،وليس العكس.
The myth of national identity and the vocabulary of coming from
أسطورة الهوية الوطنية ومفردات" قادم من"
confuses us into placing ourselves into mutually exclusive categories.
تدخلنا في متاهة وضع أنفسنا في خانات حصرية حيال بعضنا البعض.
In fact, all of us are multi -- multi-local, multi-layered.
في الواقع كل واحد منا متعدد المحلية ومتعدد الطبقات.
To begin our conversations with an acknowledgement of this complexity
بدء محادثاتنا بالاعتراف بهذا التعقيد
brings us closer together, I think, not further apart.
يقرب بعضنا لبعض،في اعتقادي، وليس العكس.
So the next time that I'm introduced,
إذا في المرة القادمة التي يتم فيه تقديمي،
I'd love to hear the truth:
أحبذ أن أسمع الحقيقة:
"Taiye Selasi is a human being, like everybody here.
"تايا سيلاسي هي إنسانة،كما الجميع هنا.
She isn't a citizen of the world, but a citizen of worlds.
هي ليست مواطنة من العالم، بل مواطنة من عدة عوالم.
She is a local of New York, Rome and Accra."
هي محلية من نيويورك،روما و أكرا."
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)